All right.
So we are going to get started now.
And I believe I've spotlighted
most of our board members.
We have a large number of us here.
So thank you folks who made it out.
This is our wrap up event for kind of
not just the conference,
but kind of where we report in
on what the ELO has been up to
for the year and have a chance to kind of
get some thoughts on some of the things
that we're thinking about.
And this year is going to be heavy on
the kind of the financial membership side,
because like every other
academic organization, we are looking at
the kind of realities
of being the same of organizations
trying to operate, to serve as large
a community as we can
of mostly kind of artist students
and those who are often
not on the most stable of incomes
and positions and trying to figure out
how to kind of be a viable organization
that serves that mission.
As we're moving forward
in a fairly difficult economic time.
And this online conference
has been a part of that,
and I'm going to speak
a little bit to it. So.
We are,
of course, kind of at the town hall.
I've tried to
all the board members who are present,
there are others who cannot be here today
with us,
but we are an all volunteer working board.
There's no one paid
to do the work of yellow in any real way.
The closest is that PD
is occasionally gotten
some small graduate stipends to help us.
But right now we don't have formal staff
in our executive director
or any of the things that a fancy large
academic organization has.
And so that's like a big part of why
we run the way we do.
It presents lots of challenges.
Filing taxes is a great joy.
There's no staff accountant.
We are kind of continually managing on
a shoestring and through the work
of the people who are on the board.
So we ask kind of for new board members.
I kind of noticed that it tends to be
people in established academic.
That's in part
because it is a service position
that only academia really recognizes,
and there is absolutely no compensation.
We expect our boards
to pay their own membership
and join the conferences and pay
for their own travel and everything else.
So this truly is kind of a volunteer run
work of passion.
And right now we're at around
kind of closing in on 300 members,
250 registrants for the conference.
We need at least 350
a year to even be a viable organization.
So we continue to struggle
with that financially.
We give out a lot of waivers of membership
because we want to have voices
here at this conference from communities
where even kind of our lowest membership
fee of 25 USD is prohibitive
because of the currency exchange.
But that does mean that
if you've been kind of hopping
into this conference on a borrowed zoom
link or did not pay your membership.
So yeah, I'd like to remind you that
there's no better time than the present
to pay your membership,
and also that this might be
the cheapest,
that it's going to be for a while.
And that is something
we would like to talk about,
not raising the membership fee
for our bottom tier.
That is $25 and will remain,
but raising some of the costs for those
who have the income to better support
the work of the organization, so that
we can continue to waive membership fees
for all those who need it.
For events like this.
And for a while,
our membership and donation
site was down early this year
because we had some problems
with our accounts due
to kind of things not having been
changed over from kind of folks
who historically had access
to those accounts.
So we have sorted that out
thanks to the work of Dean burger.
We do have kind of control of our finances
right now,
and membership and donations are open,
and we are also able to work with you.
If you do find yourself in a position
to make a larger donation,
or you've befriended
someone who's in a big
AI company and wants to show that they're
supporting artists, this is an excellent,
you know, opportunity
to give them some pretty good press.
So we're we have no pride.
We will take money from AI companies.
Absolutely.
Yes. Show them Leo's keynote.
Tell them the slide deck for the town
hall was built with plot.
Let's get anthropic in here. So
if you kind of do know
folks where you're sharing your videos
and kind of sharing the free labor
of this conference, that's a great time.
Also to encourage folks to join
because your membership is
what makes that possible.
And so here's a friendly little link
from our little yellow guy
reminding you that everything we do
can only be supported by membership.
So please
consider joining, renewing, or donating
if you have not this year especially.
As far as kind of the other work
that the organization does.
The conference is our biggest thing,
and I'll be talking more about that
in a moment.
I want to spend a little time,
of course, on this year's conference
and to thank the many, many people who
have been involved in making that happen.
But the conference is just kind of
our most visible big event every year,
and we're working on a lot of other things
through both partnerships and
projects that the board
members kind of lead and contribute
to, to, may or may not be aware of.
We, of course, had our big presentation
from the Elk five team earlier.
This.
Two days ago.
Now time has no meeting now.
Was it yesterday? I cannot tell you.
And we hosted the editorial retreat here
at the University of Central Florida.
We're so excited to be able to help
that team move forward with their work.
The electronic literature
collections are always open access.
They are targeted at pedagogy
and libraries.
They are intended to help
do some of the work of
making our history visible and keeping
some sense of structure, and also
providing helpful
and evolving answers to that question.
Some of your colleagues might still ask,
what is electronic literature anyway?
And there's nothing like those four
and now fifth volumes to help
answer that question
and also show how much has changed
and we really appreciate the work,
are also unpaid volunteer
editorial team is doing working
through hundreds of submissions,
building the whole system.
Of course, Dan Cox has built both
this year's gallery
and building the next exhibition
from our previous code,
and we just are very lucky
to have that type of support
that, frankly, we could not afford to pay
for at the level of programing
we benefit from regularly here in the El.
We also have our ongoing
Bloomsbury Electronic Literature
Series on series editorial board.
Been working with that press.
Historically, everything has been released
to open access.
That's a world that might be changing, but
there's a fantastic diversity
to what this series allows.
It's provided an official, tenure
worthy home for publications,
for both monographs and edited collections
that have really anchored the field,
and because the volumes thus far
have been open access, this is also
an incredible teaching resource.
If you haven't been taking advantage
of it, I highly recommend it.
And we have new works in that series
that speak to modern
forms, to the third generation
of electronic literature, at the growing
non Anglo centric English screen,
kind of what we used
as a conference language,
but far from the only language
for electronic literature.
So we're really also looking
to continue to grow that
like say a few words
about kind of submitting.
Yeah.
At the the series is
is always looking for new titles,
for new ideas
on what you know it might be and islet
research might look like
the latest add on is Hosni Arabic,
which you can see here
as a cover, is due out in November,
and we're very happy
that it's finally coming out.
And we will likely have a launch
in one of the salons.
But there are more in the pipeline. So.
So watch this space
and send us your ideas.
I mean, there's there's five of us
and we're always happy to comment,
even on early ideas
and wild ideas and ideas
that may not even look like a book
in the abstract.
So, you know, just send it our way.
Excellent.
Thank you.
We also are continually present
at the Modern Language Association,
and have been part
of leading conversations
on ways that you can engage
with AI ethically and thoughtfully there.
There's, of course, been kind of a number
of our events from years,
and I were responsible
for organizing the two sessions last year
that were fantastically
well attended, brought in folks
who are interested in the questions
raised by AI, and how we worked
in the digital humanities
and creative writing,
but not necessarily familiar
with the field of electronic literature.
It's also been a great recruitment
venue for us, so
please keep an eye out for our MLA
calls for submissions every year.
Even if you don't think of this
as the conference for you,
you might be really surprised.
We built a little Electronic Literature
Digital humanities sub conference
within the MLA,
and I almost never accidentally walk
into a panel where somebody yells at me
for using a computer anymore.
That's helping to kind of shift
the culture of the Modern Language
Association.
We have such incredible support
among the leadership
at MLA and folks who are really thinking
about these problems for academia
and very serious ways.
And so if you haven't been a part
of the conversations
in that space, I highly recommend it.
We are two sessions this year,
just encoding for the digital humanities,
and I showed folks who mostly
had not worked with agent tools for code
the joys of cloud code
and and the open source amenities.
In the age of AI,
we had a lot of provocations
about the importance
of thinking through local models,
small models and approaches
outside of the frontier companies
and the major AI companies
to working with these tools
and how we keep
some of the digital humanities
tools centered,
making focused structures even as edtech
offers us lots of solutions.
This year we have
two and three sessions
here and don't see, I let you.
But Mark, do you want to speak
to this year's proposed sessions?
That would be a great idea.
I will put the names of the sessions
in the chat.
Unless Alex is here, but we.
Yeah, we have two on the verge of three
sessions.
And also,
since it's going to be in Los Angeles, I'm
going to try to put together a little open
mic, open mouse.
So if you're coming out to Los Angeles,
I hope you'll join us
and participate in those. Yeah.
But yeah, I'll get I'll get those titles
in the chat for
you all.
The titles are also here on the slides.
So it's critical coding AI agency
in the Literary Imagination,
which I think speaks to a lot of the
themes that have come out in this year's
conference, prompting the avant garde,
which was absolutely brilliant at writing
and the evolution of procedural poetics
and picking up the side of the house.
And then the session
that is still pending approval,
and I hope it makes it in
because it's absolutely brilliant.
Alternate minds,
ghosts, aliens and queer limbs.
She speaks to that potential.
We have an electronic literature
to draw attention to the ways we can work
with AI outside of normative,
traditional, bias producing
frameworks to reshape.
It's really compelling,
playful and experimental ways,
and that being present at that conference
is such a powerful way
for us to be a part of the larger
conversations
that are shaping the policies
that our colleagues
are bringing to questions like tenure
and promotion in the academic space,
but also shaping how they teach
in the classroom and how they frame
generative text to students,
and how we get out of getting thrown
under the same slot bus with everyone else
producing generative text right now.
We are also thrilled to have an ongoing
partnership, kind of at the heart
of the organization with the next.
And of course, there's a featured exhibit
if you haven't checked it out.
Do you want to speak a bit to to that?
And I'm going to know
you can speak a whole hour
about the projects
you have going about the next,
but just tell us
some of the amazing things you're doing.
Thank you for for asking.
Yeah.
So we have Tell
amendment featured in an exhibition
that will run until December 15th.
We're excited about that
and know that this exhibition came about
because we realized
that Talon had not saved his work.
And the only copies were
in my personal collection and in the next.
So we are happy to have 22 works
in this exhibition,
and now we can put together a collection,
so we will be doing that next.
At the next Other things,
we're getting ready to
unleash the vast program, the vast system,
which is going to be a virtual reality
archival interaction with hypertext.
We're using Richard
Holton for Gursky is a guinea pig.
Richard's coming up in August,
and we're going to do full body
3D scan of him to put in the neck.
So when you go into the site,
you get to to talk to Richard,
that'd be kind of cool.
So we plan to do a lot of those coming
moving forward, and that we're going
to be demoing that at the hypertext
conference in September and London.
So a lot of really cool things.
And so thank you for asking.
And if you're interested in
just reach out.
And I'm happy to to chat.
And don't forget to check out
tell him how it works on screen,
which is linked from both our main
star site
and here in these town hall slides and
leave.
A link has been dropped
in the chat as well, so you have no excuse
not to go
check out all of the archival footage.
Classic works.
And I really watch the form
of all through talents
work over that time.
We also kind of been involved
in a place fellows working with cell
and the Electronic Literature
Directory, and kind of
this is part of the ongoing work of trying
to make electric literature
more findable.
There's a lot of work to be done
in this era.
We're bringing it
into the next generation.
There's thoughtful ways
to think about how AI tools are finding
and using this information to define
what electronic literature is, we hope.
And if we were working
on the financial piece,
what we hope to be bringing in
more fellows
who are interested
in doing that type of work.
So if it's something that calls to you.
We're especially interested in the ways
that we can make discoverable work
that isn't necessarily as mainstream.
I'd say the history of the large
hypertext novels and the things that
get covered in Wikipedia.
We have folks
like Dena Larson, of course, who are doing
that work of trying to increase visibility
outside of the board.
But it is kind of an ongoing challenge
for all of us
in the field to think about this work
of documentation preservation,
how that, in turn,
leads to the visibility of a history
that otherwise could quite easily be lost.
So our most visible kind of project
every year,
and the kind of the you are here
moment is the conferences.
And this this is kind of
the conclusion of the elder Lando trilogy.
It was a strange journey,
and I believe this has brought
this particular form
of the conference to its end for a while.
We are very excited
to kind of usher in some new formats,
and kind of the Orlando trilogy
was not started intentionally.
Some of you might recall
joining us in 2020, when this conference
was supposed to be actually in Orlando
and became
ill online instead,
of course.
Well, that was for horrible reasons
and was a sad,
stressful, depressing
and horrific year in many ways.
There are some valuable things we learned
from the experience of moving online,
and one of the things I wanted to
highlight, especially for those of you
who have been entrusting us with your work
in these repositories this year, is
just how much the work
from the conference circulated.
And these are Snapchat
shots of the statistics
from the two previous conferences.
And you can see the 2020 conference
with over 16,000
downloads, over 34,000 page hits,
and that's for 110 posted works,
not even including the exhibition,
which is tracked
separately from 132 countries,
and then the 2024
conference holding its own, despite
being much more recent.
At nearly 8000 downloads
or 12,000 metadata page hits,
115 posted
works and 116 countries represented.
And we
kind of continue to see that growth.
We continue to see people
using your work on syllabi,
finding and discovering things
through the conference.
Everything you've done here
that's in either any of these conference
repositories
is indexed by Google Scholar.
So it is findable by people
you might not expect.
And so we really appreciate you entrusting
kind of us with that work
so that we can make a lasting space
to invite people in.
And we already have,
I believe, like 60 of our videos
up from this conference
so far and counting.
The video team channel is flashing
behind me as I get this.
And with people working on updates
right now,
just note that with this year's videos,
the subtitles have to be added separately.
So there's someone going through
separately and adding those.
So if you haven't seen subtitles yet,
that's why.
And just know it's coming.
We are very concerned about keeping
the ongoing accessibility of the work,
and super excited
to have it available to you.
After the conference, we will announce
when the archive is fully open
and then it will remain open
for consideration in your syllabi
going forward,
just like ello 2020 and 2024.
And we are looking at kind of our largest
iteration of the Orlando series.
With this final chapter,
we have about 250 registrants.
There are 268 proceedings pages
representing our longest
such proceedings.
And remember, that's available
for you to read immediately.
It is already embedded in the Stars
repository and on the conference website.
We will also be adding
all of the proceedings
papers to the entries and stars,
so that they'll be indexed by
Google Scholar so that everyone can find
and cite your work going forward.
We have 48 works in the exhibition,
plus the guest exhibition at the next
for you to enjoy, and 110 events
that have been recorded,
and we're over halfway
through posting them.
So even after this,
even if you've been attending something
every block, you're going to have lots
of possible material
to go back and watch and learn
from when this is done.
Highly recommended for watching,
walking the dog
and catching up on the state of the field.
And I just wanted to say
that I have a lot of kind of depressingly
similar conversations
about AI at my campus,
kind of all the time,
and for understandable reasons,
the kind of the way
companies have been rolling it out,
the serious labor implications,
the total lack of environmental regulation
and how data centers are being built.
Just like constantly.
The plagiarism problem
is at the top of the list
for many of my colleagues,
and it's just been an absolute delight
to listen to the thoughtful, nuanced
kind of both critiques and engagement
here, to see everything
from putting AI in a box on a drone,
to thinking about how we can use
frontier models to build new tools
for creative practices or archive
and preserve work that might be lost.
This series of conversations,
anchored by our keynotes,
has been thoughtful and generative
in the best possible way, and I hope it's
given you some tools and resources
to take back to your campus
to remind folks
that electronic literatures
actually had a practice
where we've been thinking about generative
texts and materiality and literature
for quite a long time,
and some of the answers
that our colleagues are looking for
are here, say,
all right,
kind of interested
in having those conversations
and thinking about the ways we can be
thoughtful rather than reactionary
at moments of intense
and difficult technological change.
So, of course,
this is the obligatory part
where I try to thank everybody and fail.
But I just kind of really want to call out
that kind of
pulling off something like this
online zoom with people watching discord,
people
debugging and answering late registration
emails with the video team
working through the night.
Sending updates at 1 a.m.
requires a village, just as ello requires
a village to keep our work going.
And we've had a lot of folks
who've gone above and beyond,
most of whom are not on this call
because they're either working
or they're just completely exhausted.
So some of our anchors, of course,
John Murray, who has been handling
a lot of this with me behind the scenes
and first had the terrible idea of
let's do this a third time
so that we'd have a conference this year
and be able to do a membership drive.
Miles gains, who is working
from a completely inappropriate time
zone with us alongside Dan Cox,
who it's not only our exhibitions here,
but also has been dropping
into run tracks, moderate things, cash
fires, build the entire exhibition code
and just generally do
all of the technical things anyone ask for
in ways that keep things running.
Mike Shire, who none of you will ever see
but is seeing every single
one of these videos well, adding
the captions and subtitles back right now
to all of those files.
We have just incredible support,
and he's been leading a team of students
at cheddar.
And then, of course, among our students.
Petey has been here all the time.
You've all gotten emails from PD.
PD has also been helping out
with the ello itself,
and we'll be taking a break from that
to get his dissertation done this fall.
So please thank PD,
not just for kind of all the work he's
done on this conference
in the past to keep ello going,
but also wish him the best as he barks
on a really interesting
exploration
of AI in the literary magazine space
on his dissertation work that I know
many of you will enjoy reading.
Maybe you'll find his way
in that Bloomsbury serious someday.
Who knows.
Our proceedings here.
Jack Murray, a former student of mine,
is also not on the call.
But we told Jack, oh, maybe like,
you know,
five, six, maybe ten proceedings papers
if we're really lucky.
And you all showed up and Jack showed up
to to get those edited in the absolutely
unreasonable amount of time we left
based on the amount of labor we asked for,
our other two
missions teams contributions,
current students who should be working
on their dissertation.
But we're doing this in Stem.
Alyssa and Ricky have also popped up
in the conference moderation and hosting,
and are both working on really cool
electronic literature and performance
adjacent dissertations that I'm sure
you'll be seeing more of in the future.
And then, of course, my long suffering
now probably asleep
to colleagues Emily Johnson
and Bill Stanfill, who have been running
the other two tracks and literally
keeping the zoom fires going,
have made
all of this possible on Jason.
This group has external committee members,
but don't you worry, some of these
conference moderators don't yet,
so I will remember that
she said that in chat and send them
your way.
Also have benefited from the support
of many of you who are here.
So just our Autistic
and Scientific Committee.
ELO does not always share written reviews
and feedback,
and for understandable reasons,
it's an enormous lift to get it
organized and sent out.
And so something we really wanted
to provide for you this year
so that there would be
that peer review process
that's been part of our ELO Orlando
kind of organizing commitment,
which meant we asked a whole lot of people
to write their thoughts,
read your work, and work through
a really annoying old database system
that we use because it's free.
We don't want to
incur any unnecessary costs
for this organization.
So all of you who did those reviews,
you're on this list right now.
And just a round of applause
to many of you who are on screen.
The alphabet station is sort of odd,
but you are there.
And we group the artistic
and scientific committee
together
to try to make it fit on one side.
So many of you did both
because we asked you to do both
and we just needed that help.
You all really came through.
Thank you for that work
and are visible
and not so visible student teams.
I hope you've been thanking them
as you've gone.
Our moderators have been showing up
in every section to keep us on time,
and have done a beautiful job
of keeping us on a schedule throughout.
Our video team, of course, is working
behind the scenes constantly.
And this group, these are pretty much all
our text and technology PhD students, so
they have stepped up
in the middle of their summer
and a tremendous way,
and we are taking as many of them
who are willing out to dinner
after this to thank them as possible,
but kind of please keep in mind
that you see their names in the future.
If you have an opportunity,
support any of these students
as they're embarking upon their careers.
They all work incredibly hard and offer
so much to our field and others.
I would be remiss
if I didn't also point out that the reason
this conference is free is because UCF,
for some reason, helps me make it free.
We really want to do this conference
as a membership drive,
and not to charge you anything else,
and not to try to bring back money
into the UCF industrial complex.
And that's so important to me.
It's why looking for sponsors
is important to me,
because with the help of kind of UCF
through our center for Humanities
and Digital Research, the College of Arts
and Humanities, and the PhD program,
we were able to provide honorarium
for all of our keynote speakers
and not have any of the expenses
for running this conference or the retreat
coming out of our ellos limited budget.
And that lets us use your membership funds
to support this ongoing and important
work of education,
preservation, community building,
and hosting our next conferences.
And kind of
gives us also all of these resources,
like the free
hosting for all of these videos and things
that fundamentally would cost a lot
in a way that would make this organization
difficult to sustain.
So we benefit immensely
from the generosity
of institutions.
So thank you.
But we have exciting news for the future.
We know you've enjoyed visiting us online,
but I would like to invite,
if she's able to join us.
Maria.
Yes I'm here. Hello, everybody.
Thank you.
Please tell us a little bit of what.
What's your plan?
Yes. Hi, everyone.
Well, I'm very, very happy and also
honored for this.
Yeah,
for the trust of the electronic literature
organization
to accept our proposal to host
the next conference here
in Colombia, Universidad del Norte.
We are located
in the Caribbean coast of Colombia.
So in the north of the country,
we are looking forward
to expand the field
to connect with other networks.
For example, the Digital Humanities
Network of Colombia,
the Latin American Digital Humanities
Network, the Caribbean
Digital Humanities Network, as
we are located in the Caribbean as well.
So this is a great opportunity
for for Latin American
scholars and artists
working on the literature to
to get together, but
also to get to know you and to get to know
all the history of, of yellow and,
and build some bridges
for collaborations, for projects
I've been working with, with John,
with Mark, with Jason as well
for, for many years.
And it has been just a great opportunity
for me as a Colombian Latin
American scholar, to to learn more
and to do incredible projects.
So we are very happy.
We are also a team.
I'm not alone.
I'm working together with him.
Rodriguez from Universidad Los Andes,
which is in Bogota, the same as Nelson
Vera and Mauricio Vasquez
from a fight in Medellin.
So these are
important
universities
in one of the major cities of Colombia.
But at the same time,
we are also working with the
our master's degree here
in or in order to
of creating creative writing.
And the master is also in a process
of connecting more
with electronic literature and new media.
So it's going to be very interesting
to have also the.
Yeah, the collaboration
with the with with the master.
We are also looking forward to
do some proposals, for example,
having a space for electronic literature
in Spanish or other languages,
and also have maybe a track
for Latin American scholar, for example.
These are just ideas.
But yeah,
the idea is just to to build bridges,
to expand the field, to,
to get to know each other.
So the conference will be hybrid.
I know that in the past years
yellow has been mainly online,
which is actually great format,
but we also want to have the opportunity
to to meet in person for everybody
that that can join us here in Bahrain.
But at the same time we do not.
We have the infrastructure
to have a fully hybrid
conference running.
And also with all the recordings
for later and so on.
So for those who won't be able to
maybe travel all the way here,
don't don't worry, we will have a full
hybrid hybrid conference.
We have also many venues around the city.
The want to join us artistic venues,
for example,
the bar where Garcia marquez
used to hang out with his friends.
This is a space, a cultural space now
where we can also get together,
have maybe an exhibition
there or something like that.
We are also talking with some sponsors to,
to join us for, for the conference
and yeah, host you the host everybody
the best way and what else.
Yeah we have plenty of ideas of
for next yellow conference.
Probably the date will be announced
well in the in the next months.
But we are thinking about August
next year.
So we will keep it in the summer for you.
But we in university
we already be back in class.
So that's super nice because the campus
will be full of students
and we will have the students
attending the conference
and be part of it in the in the team
as well.
For those that
that want to, to join us. So
get ready for Colombia 2027.
And thank you again to the board
and to all the members that
are trusting us to organize
a great yellow 2027.
Thank you so much for bringing
your vision for this conference to us.
You can see the excitement in the chat
and on screen right now.
Folks are are already packing.
So this and
we're just so excited to be
taking the conference off and to be.
Everyone together again.
Your vision for the conference knots
just so delightful.
Thank you, thank you.
And the board has taken
on kind of the approach
that we need more advanced planning for
so we can have this type of in-person,
exciting conference.
We have other exciting conferences
that will be announced.
So as you're kind of thinking
about your membership and what you're
sustaining, just know that
there is a lot in store.
And we will be traveling the globe
with our upcoming conference
announcements.
So we kind of look forward to
seeing yellow travel,
perhaps even back to the
States at some point. So.
This is all in the works.
And of course,
if you want to be
a part of those types of conversations
going forward, you can always reach out
about working with the board
or helping out
with one of these conferences,
especially when you hear about one
that's coming near you.
I assure you that team is going to need
lots of help and
be plenty of opportunities
to volunteer and shape
the future of the conferences.
So with that exciting news,
I wanted to just turn things over
for a little bit
to kind of questions and concerns.
The biggest kind of new topic I'm
bringing to you as president right now
is the idea of making some slight
adjustments for income based membership.
We do not want to place any substantial
financial burden on anyone,
but we have kept the 2550 models
for a very long time, and unfortunately,
it does not go as far as it once did.
So that is something
kind of which I would love to kind of here
any any thoughts as we consider
rolling it out in 2027
with no intention of raising the bottom
level of membership costs,
we know that graduate student
stipends are, in many cases, the same
as what some of us may 20 or 30 years ago,
and they do not go as far
on institutional
support, of
course, is also vanishing in many places.
So we want to be thoughtful about that.
We also kind of want to hear more
about kind of anything you'd like to see
next or what you are doing,
so feel free to drop things
in the chat, raise a hand,
unmute and yell at us.
Whatever it is
you're looking to do.
So Dean has asked a question in the chat.
How do higher membership members
help with grants, etc.?
Grants, of course, are
trickier.
Right now
we have been looking
at some of the new private foundation
opportunities
that are related to organizations
and publishing,
and the scale of the organization
does matter for showing impacts.
So that's really
the only area where it matters.
There's a few kind of spaces
to put that information on a field,
but grants are ultimately something
where it's all about
kind of the work of showing what we do.
Can we move to something about that? In
when you write a grant,
they're not interested in funding,
structure, infrastructure.
So what they want are projects.
And so we have to have a project
to get a grant.
But it doesn't help us
with office management.
It doesn't help us with paying for,
you know, doing stipends for ELO fellows.
It's project based.
And that's one of the problems
that nonprofits face for any area, right?
Whether it's a symphony or an arts
organization that does fine art.
So we have to write grants for projects,
but then we need the infrastructure
so that we survive
so we can write the grants.
So there's a connection,
but not not like you would think.
Grant.
Grant agencies
want to know that we are self-supporting,
and we're not asking them for money
to pay our bills off.
They want to they want to know
that we can pay our own bills.
Hope that helps.
Dan is
also dropped a question in the chat.
Do you want to read that into the record,
or do you want me to be sure?
Sure folks.
So I will already tell you we have already
archived ELO 2026, the entire
online exhibition, all the media files,
everything has now been archived
as of last night,
and I have also already archived ELO 2024.
The next target is ELO 2020,
the kind of online conferences
we've done in the last six years.
Beyond that,
what I am proposing is beyond kind
of capturing websites in media.
If people want a kind
of searchable interface or something
like the Wayback Machine
that is within the realm of possibility,
that would be a larger project.
But if it is something
people would like to do, I'm just kind of
interested because right now
we just want to save everything
and then we can kind of work
through present presenting it from there.
In the chat.
The searchable would be immensely helpful.
I, I got to agree,
we're kind of at this place
where it would be really helpful
to have a meta search tool
for pulling together
some of these different histories
with something like our stars
archive is searchable,
but you could only search one conference
at a time.
Easily on all of that is a limitation
of our different proprietary systems
and little boxes that we could break down.
Is a question about how does about how
sorry.
And I were saying the same thing.
Go ahead, Lyle,
I think there's a question in the chat
about how income based membership
would work.
Yeah. Yes.
So that's something
the board has been workshopping
based on looking at other organizations
that have in place. So
the point is it would
be based on an income in the US dollars.
So for those in countries
where the income does not reach the tears
of a academic salary
and the US, nothing would change.
But as we kind of look at higher levels
of income
associated with the kind of stable
ranks of lower level
and assistant professor,
which in the US means looking at
having higher levels after the point
of a $50,000 income of very slight,
but then a much higher level
for those of us
who are fortunate enough
to work in institutions
where we make $100,000,
and really having the tier system
that starts at that point of assistant
professor in the US
and is really looking to tax the rich.
So someone like me, who is a stable, full
professor at an institution where I earn
quite a lot, is perfectly capable
of paying
a much higher membership fee than
someone who was an instructor
in another country
where the income I, especially
with currency exchange, is not comparable
to even our assistant professor. And
so we are not looking to make changes
at the lower levels.
But we are looking at you
full professors and associate professors,
and those of us
who have the ability to provide
a bit more to stay in the organization.
And we will send out an announce
and welcome community
feedback on the specific amounts.
But you could get a pretty clear sense
from our vision there
of looking at.
Income levels at those ranks me less.
Asking for more from our higher tier
folks who have also
those of us who are in full professor
have benefited so much kind of
from the resources of the field,
from the existence of the field,
that it is really fair
for us to contribute back.
And there are already some of us who do.
As TD points out, we already benefits of
stash from folks who do that informally.
But one of the things
that changing the membership level allows
is for folks to use institutional money
to pay their membership fee
at the higher amount,
instead of just donating personally.
So it's actually a bit sneaky in that,
and it's based on your current income,
not on what your income
was at the point of retirement.
So retiree is not if you are
to have a
pension, if you're from that generation,
then yes.
If you're going to retire
like the average millennial
right now, then no.
We're not really sure what retirement is.
We're pretty sure it's when they put us
into the bot network as a battery,
or it's going to be something
like out of ghost in the shell.
That's a solid state reference.
For those of you
who've gone down that rabbit hole.
Yeah.
All right. Great.
I entertain one person.
Yes. Yeah.
Sorry if this is a little
blunt.
I'm not ruining my career prospects here.
I'm grateful for the work
the organizers did.
And some of the challenges around
positioning in relation to AI
and the digital conferencing.
Yeah, maybe
come from that undue burden post put on
UCF folks.
But.
But this was not a neutral
or critical space in content or in form
with regard to AI,
tech, industry and national agendas.
Let me list some of the examples. Right.
First, it's just the cloud based
sort of entry points,
applications and forms which are fun.
A lot of them kind of break
like the cute animation of yellow,
like crashes the browser every so often,
like a lot of cloud, but whatever.
It's fun
to have all these additional features.
It is also a choice to say
we're fine with that,
but that's still relatively minor.
I think there's a number of other spaces
and judgment that creates this deep
feeling of disconnect in this moment.
I don't necessarily
expect the organization to take a unified,
consensus style position on.
The questions around
who gets to participate in scholarship,
what it means,
and what it's about in the year 2026,
in under the, you know,
watchful gaze of the United States
government and culture.
The problem is
then there's these additional features
where it's and there's AI transcription
and recording.
Again,
there's an accessibility benefit there.
But once again, we're told implicitly,
without necessarily choice on the matter
that were part of
or like willing to turn on these US
based surveillance networks
and then the keynotes
and the other choices, again,
by by wonderful artists, generous people,
a kind community again and again
make this point
about moral panics, reactionary views
from encountering your colleagues.
And this is the kind of space
where we can, like, let our guard down.
But I'm not comfortable in this version
of the space,
because all those points may be fair
for scholarship
and should remain within the venues.
I don't think the counterpoint was made
maybe at the edges
in a couple of the talks,
but there was a choice that we
there is a
position being put forward
about the inevitability of technology
and the role of the scholar
to sort of like,
create
some speculative criticisms around it.
And there's just this mismatch
between the grievance
of being sort of dismissed artistically
or intellectually for playing with AI
and the fear of being thrown in a cage.
And I don't think that's very personal
for for me, per se.
But it is like during this conference,
I'm reading news about how
anti-imperialist, left wing and so on,
and other groups are now classified
as terrorists under your law there.
So so that's the backdrop.
Again, we don't have to talk about
the news and the politics.
But in that backdrop,
the choice to talk about AI
as if business was as usual
and like every now and then,
say something about the interesting option
of open models
when everyone's doing things in clod is
is a very constraining choice and a very
whether conscious
or not, it's reinforcing, I think, a kind
of separation, maybe between the main line
of the electric literature community
and other like new media code poetics
kind of communities
that take a more critical position,
and that is what it is.
But this is the community I first found
and it is difficult.
So sorry to editorialized there.
But I think
the question is how you reflect
on creating
a neutral space in a space where those who
because as you all allude to,
right, you, you acknowledge the problem
facing scholarship.
Okay, maybe here's where I'll close.
Sorry.
After McDade gave some comments,
I think distilled like the position
a lot of the scholars here
have that this is the continuity
of the last 40 years, and that's okay.
There's no reason to be scared.
But if you're in Chile in 1973,
when the International telegraph
and telecommunications
company was highly involved in
and paying money to support the coup
and then large scale killings
of of, of activists and Chile,
then you have every reason to see
the other side of what submission
to this particular network is.
And I again, sorry for the bluntness
and putting these things
on this table in that way.
And it's not highly practical
to say or okay.
The, the question is just without
because maybe you can't speaking
to that context in total like
how do you relate to the yellow
becoming the community
where AI art is welcome,
and how do you hold on to sort of critical
possibility,
while also like institutionalizing
the use of Silicon Valley,
big Tech and the surveillance capitalism
in every aspect
of organizational practice?
I suspect a lot of people
are going to want to respond to that,
but I want to kind of just take a moment
to point out that I think the very fact
you feel confident to come up
and bring that point,
to raise critique of the tools we're
using in the platforms
is one of the strengths of yellow.
I'm glad you did.
And that's an important part of what
I think this organization
enables as a community.
There's also kind of a lot of realities
of how institutions work.
And the platforms were on that have been
embedded in this from the beginning.
What does it mean to create electronic
literature that you share on Twitter?
What does it mean
to still have accounts on Twitter?
I'm sorry x there.
What does it mean
that we announce our events on Facebook
and that we still use Meta's platforms,
when it might be one of the most
monstrous people?
Like we are constantly using the tools
of surveillance capitalism.
We are trapped in them.
I would love to host an online conference
that used entirely open source tools
and local models running on our server
for the AI transcription,
and didn't rely on your CS infrastructure.
I have a great deal of distrust
in UCF's infrastructure.
Hi UCF
and share
many of your concerns on that point.
I also believe that
it is the only accessible,
sustainable infrastructure
we have right now for that purpose,
and certainly the only one
that we can afford to
add the cost of free
as provided by the institution.
A similar
reality shows on all of the labor
of the conference,
and cloud code happens to be
a tool that I find very useful
for things like this slide deck.
It has actually freed me
of the constraints of other proprietary
platforms that I hate more,
like PowerPoint.
We make our trade offs, PowerPoint
and WordPress at low and very particular
design choices
and their own controls and their own
in the file size.
Their own resistance to being archived.
All sorts of things that I didn't want
when I was thinking
about making things in HTML.
And so there's kind of always trade offs.
I believe Leo said it
best in his earlier, when he reminded us
that there is no ethical consumption
under capitalism.
But I will just say, as an employee of a
public institution in the state of Florida
where my speech is regulated,
my syllabi are surveilled,
my students are in some cases
terrified about their own dissertation
topics or putting the name of their talk
on their travel registration form.
I share many of your concerns.
I also think that our
leadership in AI as a field
is one of the things that we can hold to
to help many of the folks in this room
keep jobs and students and programs.
So it's not something
I'm willing to give up
because I think we can help people
use it better.
And I hope that
even if you found kind of
some of this unbiased
this to not be as unbiased
as you would like, that
you appreciate the work
that many people are trying to do,
and sustaining the field
and having opportunities for grad students
and bringing faculty
into English departments
as part of the excitement around AI.
Thinking about the ways that we can still
have humanities in a field as a result.
That we both model.
I'm sorry.
Samya has a hand up.
Yeah. Hi.
Am I audible?
Yes. Yeah.
Thank you so much
for for bringing
some of these conversations up.
And I feel that this is a strength
that I have also benefited from immensely.
Being a part of this community
for the last half a decade,
and it stands right now,
I would like to use this platform
for a call for help, to be very honest,
because for the last five years
I have been running a community with my
very close and special colleagues,
some of whom are in this room as well
called electronic Literature India.
And the reason
why I use the term electronic literature
and not other forms of interactivity
in my title,
is that I am trained
in the field of literature in itself,
and I see a huge amount of value
in incorporating digital
within literary studies and humanities,
especially to diversify
the curriculum and introduce
these possibility to students,
especially in Global South countries
like India.
However, even after five years,
we are still dominated
heavily by early career individuals
like myself
and PhD students mostly, and we lack
a severe amount of infrastructure
even to host and maintain decent
events, a website or things like that.
And I would like to reiterate
that it would be good
to collaborate
in whatever instance is possible
with the electronic organization
and other such a light bodies
so that we could sustain
our infrastructures together.
Because I feel that with whatever little
I have done and other people like me
have done with being raised by the yellow
in some sense, shape or form,
my dissertation suddenly wouldn't have
existed without the yellow.
And I believe that I have
also contributed
back to the yellow in some sense.
And now I would hope that we can build
these infrastructures together
and take it forward in some way.
So that is the call.
I hope that
I can get some help out there,
and we can take
some of these global conversations
forward.
If we do working groups.
I just want to kind of comet that we do
not tend to have formal working groups,
which we've got the working board,
and it is already,
frankly, hard to convene that board.
But we do have project teams
on things like VLC.
And certainly if you're interested
in bringing a project to the board
and finding ways for us to support us
through kind of through that project,
we'd be happy to take out mechanisms
for support and do what we can
with the understanding that we are
a small working
board of people who volunteer, and
we operate on a tiny amount of membership
funding to do the best we can.
Do you want
to speak a bit to what you posted?
About the yellow board
being the working group or the other one?
The or so?
Caleb
is just such a good one
that I was calling you out for.
But if you don't want to know, no.
Happy to, happy to, you know, Ursula
again, like one of my literary
heroes, right?
Like amazing, amazing writer wrote
a very powerful short story
that's almost like an essay.
A thought experiment on the
just the impossible
ethical choices that that sometimes
society thrusts upon us.
I mean, listen, I like the yellow.
I'll just say this.
I was planning to propose
an elbow conference here
at my home institution in North Carolina,
and I did not feel like it.
Support.
Like I made a choice
not to, like, support this country
as a place to host a conference,
a face to face conference for the yellow.
Not at this time.
I'm hoping that the situation will improve
and and that I can
then feel comfortable
to bring folks to my home institution.
So so I mean, you know, Liggins story,
the ones who walk away from Amelia's,
if you haven't read it, it's a short one.
It it it presents
this seemingly utopian society.
It's and discusses, right.
Like what might make a utopian society.
But at the heart of that society
there is abuse.
There is a almost a sacrificial figure
within it, and it is a child.
And it is something that the society
reckons with.
And, and and she talks
about how the society confronts
these ethical choices
and how some walk away from that society.
And, you know, like, I'm
not saying that ello is Amelia's
or anything like that,
but think of any space, any technology,
any country, any society,
any set of ethical choices that we make.
Some we walk away from, some
we understand and accept and stay with.
And this does not mean we don't critique.
This does not mean we don't try to make
this a better place and try to mitigate.
But but again,
it's it's a really powerful story.
I don't want to say more.
I just
you should read it and reflect upon it.
And you know, again,
yeah, we are every day
confronted with difficult ethical choices.
And and I think, as I said in my keynote,
it's important
to respect other people's
ethical choices as well.
And I mean, we can disagree, right?
But let's respect
the hard fought decisions that we make.
And once again, I feel
Leo has provided us with a perfect words
to end on.
There's some discussion of the need
for an AI and ethical use or ethics
and AI ese sign
or something over in the chat,
which I'm
sure some collective will take up,
but well, the board has supported
publishing practice.
We do not ourselves
try to take on additional publishing
outside of the conference,
so I hope someone will take up that call
and make something that will help
everyone think through a difficult moment.
Thank you again to all the board
and to the conference team.
I this kind of concludes
the conference teams may work
and we shift over to the award
ceremony run by members
who have been doing
an incredible amount of work
to make this possible.
Just a ridiculous amount of work.
So well, thank Jason and Advance.
And I also want to give them
a few moments to prepare.
So I'm going to stop this recording.
I'm not going to close the room.
We're just going to leave
these two last sessions group together.
But I do want to let everyone
take a moment to stretch.
We'll start up the awards promptly at 445.